<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc1034 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc1035 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5358 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5358.xml'>
  <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-terminology PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-terminology.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" updates="1035"
  docName="draft-jabley-dnsop-refuse-any-00">

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Minimal Responses for ANY Queries">Providing
      Minimal-Sized Responses to DNS Queries with QTYPE=ANY</title>

    <author initials='J.' surname="Abley" fullname='Joe Abley'>
      <organization>Dyn, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>103-186 Albert Street</street>
          <city>London</city>
          <region>ON</region>
          <code>N6A 1M1</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 519 670 9327</phone>
        <email>jabley@dyn.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="O." surname="Gudmundsson" fullname="Olafur Gudmundsson">
      <organization>CloudFlare Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>olafur@cloudflare.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="M." surname="Majkowski" fullname="Marek Majkowski">
      <organization>CloudFlare Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>marek@cloudflare.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="19" month="September" year="2015"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Domain Name System (DNS) specifies a query type (QTYPE)
        "ANY". The operator of an authoritative DNS server might choose
        not to respond to such queries for reasons of local policy,
        motivated by security, performance or other reasons.</t>

      <t>The DNS specification does not include specific guidance
	for the behaviour of DNS servers or clients in this situation.
        This document aims to provide such guidance.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This document uses terminology specific to the Domain Name
        System (DNS), descriptions of which can be found in
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-terminology"/>.</t>

      <t>In this document, "ANY Query" refers to a DNS query with
        QTYPE=ANY.</t>

      <t>In an exchange of DNS messages between two hosts, this document
        refers to the host sending a DNS request as the initiator, and
        the host sending a DNS response as the responder.</t>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
        "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY"
        and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Domain Name System (DNS) specifies a query type (QTYPE)
        "ANY". The operator of an authoritative DNS server might choose
        not to respond to such queries for reasons of local policy,
        motivated by security, performance or other reasons.</t>

      <t>The DNS specification <xref target="RFC1034"/> <xref
        target="RFC1035"/> does not include specific guidance
	for the behaviour of DNS servers or clients in this situation.
	This document aims to provide such guidance.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Motivations">
      <t>ANY queries are legitimately used for debugging and checking
	the state of a DNS server for a particular owner name. ANY
	queries are sometimes used as a attempt to reduce the number
	of queries needed to get information, e.g. to obtain MX, A
	and AAAA RRSets for a mail domain in a single query, although
	there is no documented guidance available for this use case
	and some implementations have been observed that appear not
	to function as perhaps their developers expected.</t>

      <t>ANY queries are also frequently used to exploit the amplification
        potential of DNS servers using spoofed source addresses and
        UDP transport (see <xref target="RFC5358"/>). Having the ability
        to return small responses to such queries makes DNS servers
        less attractive amplifiers.</t>

      <t>ANY queries are sometimes used to help mine authoritative-only
	DNS servers for zone data, since they return all RRSets for
	a particular owner name. A DNS server operator might prefer
	not to send conventional ANY responses to reduce the potential
	for such information leaks.</t>

      <t>Some authoritative-only DNS server implementations require
	additional processing in order to send a conventional
	response to an ANY query, and avoiding that processing
	expense may be desirable.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Impact on Recursive Resolvers"> 
      <t>Alternative proposals for dealing with ANY queries have been
	discussed. One approach proposed using a new RCODE to signal
	that an authortitaive server did not answer ANY queries in
	the standard way. This approach was found to have an
	undesirable effect on both resolvers and authoritative-only
	servers; resolvers receiving an unknown RCODE caused them
	to re-send the same query to all available authoritative
	servers, rather than suppress future such ANY queries for
	the same QNAME.</t>

      <t>This proposal avoids that outcome by returning an RRSet
        in the response to an ANY query, providing resolvers with
        something to cache and effectively suppressing repeat queries
        to the same or different authority servers.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Behaviour of DNS Responders" anchor="responder">
      <t>A DNS responder which receives an ANY query MAY
	decline to provide a conventional response, and instead
	send a response with a single HINFO resource record in the
	answer section.  The CPU field of the HINFO RDATA SHOULD
	be set to RFCXXXX [note to RFC Editor, replace with RFC
	number assigned to this document].  The OS field of the
	HINFO RDATA SHOULD be set to the null string to minimise
	the size of the response.</t>

      <t>If the DNS query includes DO=1 and the QNAME corresponds
	to a zone that is known by the responder to be signed, valid
	RRSIG resource records MAY be returned. However, the responder
	MAY return an unsigned answer; a validating initiator that
	sends a subsequent explicit query with QTYPE=HINFO will
	receive a signed proof that the HINFO does not exist or a
	signed HINFO RRSet, either of which can be cached to suppress
	repeated queries.</t>

      <t>Except as described in this section, the DNS responder
	MUST follow the standard algorithms when constructing a
	response.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Behaviour of DNS Initiators">
      <t>XXX consider whether separate text here is required depending
        on whether the initiator is a non-caching stub resolver or
        a caching recursive resolver.</t>

      <t>A DNS initator which sends a query with QTYPE=ANY and
        receives a response containing an HINFO, as described in
	<xref target="responder"/>, MAY cache the HINFO response
	in the normal way. Such cached HINFO resource records SHOULD
	be retained in the cache following normal caching semantics,
	as it would with any other response received from a DNS
	responder.</t>

      <t>A DNS initiator MAY suppress queries with QTYPE=ANY in the
        event that the local cache contains a matching HINFO resource
        record with RDATA.CPU as described in <xref target="responder"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Changes to RFC 1035">
      <t>It is important to note that returning a subset of available
	RRSets when processing an ANY query is legitimate and
	consistent with <xref target="RFC1035"/>; ANY does not mean
	ALL.</t>

      <t>This document describes optional behaviour for both DNS
        initators and responders, and implementation of the guidance
        provided by this document is OPTIONAL.</t>

      <t>XXX more words here about any updates implied to RFC 1035,
        or delete the section if it turns out that, in the final
        analysis, there are none.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Queries with QTYPE=ANY are frequently observed as part of
	reflection attacks, since a relatively small query can be
	used to elicit a large response; this is a desirable
	characteristic if the goal is to maximise the amplification
	potential of a DNS server as part of a volumetric attack.
	The ability of a DNS operator to suppress such responses
	on a particular server makes that server a less useful
	amplifier.</t>

      <t>The optional behaviour described in this document to reduce
        the size of responses to queries with QTYPE=ANY is compatible
        with the use of DNSSEC by both initiator and responder.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Your name here, etc.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc1034;
      &rfc1035;
      &rfc2119;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc5358;

      &I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-terminology;
    </references>

    <section title="Editorial Notes">
      <t>This section (and sub-sections) to be removed prior to
        publication.</t>

      <section title="Venue">
        <t>An appropriate forum for discussion of this draft is
          the dnsop working group.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Change History">
        <section title="draft-jabley-dnsop-ordered-answers-00">
          <t>Initial draft circulated for comment.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>

