<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [
	  <!ENTITY rfc1034 PUBLIC '' 
		   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc1035 PUBLIC ''
		   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
		   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc5358 PUBLIC ''
		   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5358.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc6895 PUBLIC ''
		   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6895.xml'>
	  <!ENTITY rfc7719 PUBLIC ''
		   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7719.xml'>
	  ]>

<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" updates="1035"
  docName="draft-ietf-dnsop-refuse-any-04">

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Minimal Responses for ANY Queries">Providing
      Minimal-Sized Responses to DNS Queries that have QTYPE=ANY</title>


    <author initials='J.' surname="Abley" fullname='Joe Abley'>
      <organization>Dyn, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>103-186 Albert Street</street>
          <city>London</city>
          <region>ON</region>
          <code>N6A 1M1</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 519 670 9327</phone>
        <email>jabley@dyn.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="O." surname="Gudmundsson" fullname="Olafur Gudmundsson">
      <organization>Cloudflare Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>olafur+ietf@cloudflare.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="M." surname="Majkowski" fullname="Marek Majkowski">
      <organization>Cloudflare Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>marek@cloudflare.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="08" month="February" year="2017"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Domain Name System (DNS) specifies a query type (QTYPE)
        "ANY". The operator of an authoritative DNS server might choose
        not to respond to such queries for reasons of local policy,
        motivated by security, performance or other reasons.</t>

      <t>The DNS specification does not include specific guidance
	for the behaviour of DNS servers or clients in this situation.
        This document aims to provide such guidance.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Domain Name System (DNS) specifies a query type (QTYPE)
        "ANY". The operator of an authoritative DNS server might choose
        not to respond to such queries for reasons of local policy,
        motivated by security, performance or other reasons.</t>

      <t>The DNS specification <xref target="RFC1034"/> <xref
        target="RFC1035"/> does not include specific guidance
	for the behaviour of DNS servers or clients in this situation.
	This document aims to provide such guidance.</t>
    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This document uses terminology specific to the Domain Name
        System (DNS), descriptions of which can be found in
        <xref target="RFC7719"/>.</t>

      <t>In this document, "ANY Query" refers to a DNS meta-query with
        QTYPE=ANY. An "ANY Response" is a response to such a query.</t>

      <t>In an exchange of DNS messages between two hosts, this document
        refers to the host sending a DNS request as the initiator, and
        the host sending a DNS response as the responder.</t>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
        "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY"
        and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Motivations">
      <t>ANY queries are legitimately used for debugging and checking
	the state of a DNS server for a particular name. ANY
	queries are sometimes used as a attempt to reduce the number
	of queries needed to get information, e.g. to obtain MX, A
	and AAAA RRSets for a mail domain in a single query. Although
	there is no documented guidance available for this use case
	and some implementations have been observed that appear not
	to function as perhaps their developers expected. For any
	developer that assumes that ANY query will be sent to
	authoritative server to fetch all RRSets, they need to include
	a fallback when that does not happen.</t>

      <t>ANY queries are also frequently used to exploit the amplification
        potential of DNS servers/resolvers using spoofed source addresses and
        UDP transport (see <xref target="RFC5358"/>). Having the ability
        to return small responses to such queries makes DNS servers
        less attractive amplifiers.</t>
      <t>ANY queries are sometimes used to help mine authoritative-only
	DNS servers for zone data, since they are expected to return all RRSets for
	a particular query name. If a DNS operator prefers to reduce
	the potential for information leaks, they MAY choose to 
	not to send large ANY responses.</t>

      <t>Some authoritative-only DNS server implementations require
	additional processing in order to send a conventional
	ANY response, and avoiding that processing
	expense might be desirable.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="General Approach"> 
      <t>This proposal provides a mechanism for an authority server
	to signal that conventional ANY queries are not supported
	for a particular QNAME, and to do so in such a way that
	is both compatible with and triggers desirable behaviour by
        unmodified clients (e.g. DNS resolvers).</t>

      <t>Alternative proposals for dealing with ANY queries have been
	discussed. One approach proposed using a new RCODE to signal
	that an authoritative server did not answer ANY queries in
	the standard way. This approach was found to have an
	undesirable effect on both resolvers and authoritative-only
	servers; resolvers receiving an unknown RCODE caused them
	to re-send the same query to all available authoritative
	servers, rather than suppress future such ANY queries for
	the same QNAME.</t>

      <t>This proposal avoids that outcome by returning a non-empty
	RRSet in the ANY response, providing resolvers
	with something to cache and effectively suppressing repeat
	queries to the same or different authority servers.</t>
    </section>

   <section title="Behaviour of DNS Responders" anchor="responder">
      <t>Below are the three different modes of behaviour
        by DNS responders for names that exists that are used, listed
        in the order of preference.  
	Operators/Implementers are free to choose  
        whichever mechanism best suits their environment.
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>A DNS responder can choose to select one or subset of
            RRSets at the QNAME.  </t>

          <t>A DNS responder can return a synthesised HINFO
            resource record. 
	    See <xref target="hinfo"/> for discussion of the
            use of HINFO.</t>
	  <t>Resolver can try to give out the most likely records the
	  requester wants. This is not always possible and the likely
	  RRsets may add up to a large answer. </t> 
        </list>
      </t> 

      <t>Except as described below in this section, the DNS responder
	MUST follow the standard algorithms when constructing a
	response.
      </t>

      <section title="Select one RRSet mode">

	<t>A DNS responder which receives an ANY query MAY decline
	  to provide a conventional response, or MAY instead send a
	  response with a single RRSet in the answer section.</t>
	
	<t>The RRSet returned in the answer section of the response
	  MAY be a single RRSet owned by the name specified in the
	  QNAME. Where multiple RRSets exist, the responder SHOULD choose
	  a small one(s) to reduce its amplification potential.</t>
	<t>If the zone is signed RRSIG records MUST be included in the
	answer
	</t>
      </section> 

      <section title="Synthesised HINFO RRset"> 
	<t>If there is no CNAME present at the owner name matching
	  the QNAME, the resource record returned in the response MAY
	  instead be synthesised, in which case a single HINFO resource
	  record SHOULD be returned.  The CPU field of the HINFO RDATA
	  SHOULD be set to RFCXXXX [note to RFC Editor, replace with
	  RFC number assigned to this document].  The OS field of the
	  HINFO RDATA SHOULD be set to the null string to minimize
	  the size of the response.</t>

	<t>The TTL encoded for a synthesised RR SHOULD be chosen by the
          operator of the DNS responder to be large enough to suppress
          frequent subsequent ANY queries from the same initiator with
          the same QNAME, understanding that a TTL that is too long
          might make policy changes relating to ANY queries difficult
          to change in the future. The specific value used is hence
          a familiar balance when choosing TTL for any RR in any zone,
          and be specified according to local policy.</t>
	
	<t>If the DNS query includes DO=1 and the QNAME corresponds
	  to a zone that is known by the responder to be signed, a valid
	  RRSIG for the RRSets in the answer (or authority if answer is
	  empty) section MUST be returned.  In the case of DO=0, the RRSIG SHOULD be
	  omitted.</t> 
      </section> 
      <section title="Guess intention"> 
	<t>In some cases it is possible to guess what the initiator
	wants in the answer but not always. Some implementations have
	implemented the spirit of this document by returning all of
	CNAME or (MX A and AAAA) RRsets that are present. This is
	not a guess but a heuristic that seems to work well in
	practice. The main drawback is the size of the answer. 
	</t> 
	<t>As in the first one if the zone is signed RRSIG MUST be
	returned if there the DO bit is set on query. 
	</t> 
      </section> 
      <section title="Responding to queries over TCP"> 
	<t>There has been a desire to specify that a ANY query over
	TCP get full response. This document does not specify that as
	that is best left to the operator to decide. Implementers SHOULD
	provide an option for operators to specify behavior over TCP. 
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Behaviour of DNS Initiators">
      <t>A DNS initiator which sends a query with QTYPE=ANY and
        receives a response containing an HINFO resource record or a
        single RRset, as described in 	<xref target="responder"/>,
        MAY cache the response in the normal way. Such cached resource records SHOULD 
	be retained in the cache following normal caching semantics,
	as it would with any other response received from a DNS
	responder.</t>

      <t>A DNS initiator MAY suppress queries with QTYPE=ANY in the
	event that the local cache contains a matching HINFO resource
	record with RDATA.CPU field, as described in <xref
	target="responder"/>.
	Similarly it is fine to replay back exactly what Authoritative
	server returned to ANY query. 
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="HINFO Considerations" anchor="hinfo">
      <t>It is possible that the synthesised HINFO RRSet in an ANY response, once
	cached by the initiator, might suppress subsequent queries
	from the same initiator with QTYPE=HINFO. Thus the use of HINFO in this proposal would
	hence have effectively mask the HINFO RRSet present in
	the zone.
      </t>

      <t>Authority-server operators who serve zones that rely upon
	conventional use of the HINFO RRTYPE SHOULD sensibly choose
	the "single RRset" method described in this document or
	select another type.</t>

      <t>The HINFO RRTYPE is believed to be rarely used in the DNS
	at the time of writing, based on observations made at
	recursive servers, authority servers and in passive DNS.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Updates to RFC 1035">
      <t>It is important to note that returning a subset of available
	RRSets when processing an ANY query is legitimate and
	consistent with <xref target="RFC1035"/>; ANY does not mean
	ALL. The main difference here is that the TC bit SHOULD not be set
	on the response indicating that this is not a complete answer.
      </t>

      <t>This document describes optional behaviour for both DNS
        initiators and responders, and implementation of the guidance
        provided by this document is OPTIONAL.</t>

      <t>RRSIG queries have the same potential as ANY queries of
	generating large answers as well as extra work. DNS
	implementations are free to not return all RRSIG records. In the wild
	there are implementations that return REFUSE, others return
	single RRSIG, etc. This document recommends returning a single
	RRSIG in this case.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Implementation Experience"> 
      <t> In October 2015 Cloudflare Authoritative Name server
      implementation implemented the HINFO response. Few minor
      problems have been reported and worked out. NSD has for a while
      implemented a sub-set response. A Bind user implemented this
      draft suggestion of returning only single RRset during an
      attack, his code is now in the current release.
      </t> 
    </section> 

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Queries with QTYPE=ANY are frequently observed as part of
	reflection attacks, since a relatively small query can be
	used to elicit a large response; this is a desirable
	characteristic if the goal is to maximize the amplification
	potential of a DNS server as part of a volumetric attack.
	The ability of a DNS operator to suppress such responses
	on a particular server makes that server a less useful
	amplifier.</t>

      <t>The optional behaviour described in this document to reduce
        the size of responses to queries with QTYPE=ANY is compatible
        with the use of DNSSEC by both initiator and responder.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The IANA is requested to update the <eref
        target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/dns-parameters/dns-parameters.xhtml#dns-parameters-4">Resource
        Record (RR) TYPEs Registry</eref> entry as follows:</t>

      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Type</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Value</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Meaning</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

        <c>*</c>
        <c>255</c>
        <c>A request for some or all records the server has available</c>
        <c><xref target="RFC1035"/><xref target="RFC6895"/>
          [This Document]</c>
      </texttable>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Evan Hunt and David Lawrence provided valuable
      observations and concrete suggestions. Jeremy Laidman helped
      make the document better. Tony Finch realized that this document was
      valuable and implemented it while under attack. A large number
      of people have provided comments and suggestions we thank them
      all for the feedback. </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc1034;
      &rfc1035;
      &rfc2119;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc5358;
      &rfc6895;

      &rfc7719;
    </references>

    <section title="Editorial Notes">
      <t>This section (and sub-sections) to be removed prior to
        publication.</t>

      <section title="Change History">
	<section title="draft-ietf-dnsop-refuse-any-04">
	  <t>These are the changes requested during WGLC. 
	    The title has been updated for readability
	    The behavior section now contains description of three
	    different approaches in order of preference.
	    Text added on behavior over TCP. 
	    The document is clear in how it updates from  RFC1035. 
	    Minor adjustments for readability and remove redundancy. 
	  </t>
	</section>
	<section title="draft-ietf-dnsop-refuse-any-03">
	  <t> Change section name to "Updates to RFC1034", few minor
	  grammar changes suggested by Matthew Pounsett and Tony Finch.</t>
	  <t> Text clarifications, reflecting experience, added
	  implementation experience. 
	  </t>
	</section> 
	<section title="draft-ietf-dnsop-refuse-any-02">
	  <t>Added suggestion to call out RRSIG is optional when
	  DO=0.</t>
	  <t>Number of text suggestions from Jeremy Laidman </t> 
	</section>
        <section title="draft-ietf-dnsop-refuse-any-01">
          <t>Add IANA Considerations</t>
        </section>

        <section title="draft-ietf-dnsop-refuse-any-00">
          <t>Re-submitted with a different name following adoption
            at the dnsop WG meeting convened at IETF 94.</t>
        </section>

	<section title="draft-jabley-dnsop-refuse-any-01"> 
	  <t>Make signing of RRSets in answers from signed
	    zones mandatory.</t>

          <t>Document the option of returning an existing RRSet
            in place of a synthesised one.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="draft-jabley-dnsop-refuse-any-00">
          <t>Initial draft circulated for comment.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>

